I've been asking this question of all the AI researchers I interview.
对于所有来面试的人工智能研究员 我都会问一个问题
What is your definition of artificial intelligence?
你对人工智能的定义是什么？
&gt;&gt; To me, AI is programming a computer to do the right thing
对我而言 人工智能就是给计算机编程 让其做正确的事情
when you don't know for sure what the right thing is.
哪怕你自己并不确定这正确的事是什么
&gt;&gt; So Peter, you've written the most widely used AI textbook in history.
那么 Peter 你撰写了史上使用最广的人工智能教科书
Can you tell us about that process and what led to its success?
你能跟我们说说写书的过程以及这本书为什么能大获成功吗？
Well, around 1990, I remember the AI faculty at Berkeley,
在 1990 年左右 我还记得在伯克利
we all went to lunch together.
我和那里的教职员总是一起吃午饭
And we were lamenting that none of the textbooks available at that time were
我们对当时市面上没有一本教科书
quite what we wanted.
符合我们的需求而感到可惜
And we should write a new text, we said, but it didn't happen.
所以我们说要自己写本新的教科书 但是没有写成
I ended up leaving Berkeley,
我离开了伯克利
and I went into industry, first with Sun Microsystems.
进入了业内 一开始我去了太阳微系统公司
About a year later, I saw Stuart Russell at a conference.
大概一年后 我在一次会议上遇见了 Stuart Russel
And I said, well,
我就说
you guys must be almost done with that book you were always talking about.
你们肯定快写好当时老说的那本书了吧
And he said, no, they hadn't done anything.
他说没有 他们什么都没写
So I said, well, the two of us should just go ahead and do it, and we did.
我说那我们两个来写吧 于是我们就动手了
I think the book was successful because of a fortuitous accident of timing.
我觉得这本书的成功是时运使然
We happened to come along just as AI was making this
我们恰好撞上了
transition from Boolean logic to probability,
人工智能从布尔逻辑过渡到概率学的时期
and from handcrafted knowledge to machine learning.
也是从手工知识到机器学习的过渡期
And so
所以
we were able to capture that in our book in a way that wasn't in previous books.
我们抓住这一点 将其与书中内容结合起来 这是之前的教科书都没有的
&gt;&gt; Your intro to AI course has had over 160,000 students, and
你那人工智能入门课的学员超过了 16 万
led to the founding of Udacity.
也促成了优达学城
Why did you and Sebastian decide to do the course in the first place?
是什么促使你和 Sebastian 决定开办这门课程的？
&gt;&gt; Well, we taught the intro to AI course at Stanford in 2010,
2010 年 我们在斯坦福上了这门人工智能入门课
a regular course in the classroom.
那是学校的一门常规课程
And then in winter 2011, I guess they couldn't come up with anyone
然后在 2011 年的冬天 我想他们应该是找不到其他人来教这门课吧
else to teach the course, so they asked us to do it again, and we agreed.
所以他们让我们再上一次 我们同意了
But since we had just done it,
但既然之前已经上过了这门课
we decided we wanted to do something different this time.
我们决定这次要来点不同的
And Sebastian suggested opening the course up to the world.
Sebastian 建议让课程面向全世界
I thought, that's a great idea.
我觉得这是个好主意
Maybe we might get 1,000 students to sign up.
或许我们能收获一千个注册学员呢
Well, I was off by two orders of magnitude.
结果多了两个数量级
&gt;&gt; Wow.
哇
What lessons did you learn from being the head of search quality for
早期在谷歌任职搜索质量经理的时候
Google in the early days?
你学到了些什么？
&gt;&gt; I think one important lesson is, pay attention to the data.
我觉得自己学到的最重要一点是 关注数据
Understand what's out there, what you're doing, and how well you're doing.
了解外面有什么 知道你自己在做什么、做得怎么样
Keep experimenting and measuring how well you're doing,
不断尝试并衡量自己做事的水平
and that way, you can improve.
这样你就能进步
And two, pay attention to people.
第二是关注人
I think we did a good job at building a high-quality search engine.
我觉得我们打造了个很高质的搜索引擎
But it all comes down to having great people and keeping them happy and
但归根结底与吸引优秀人群
productive.
让他们开心、高产分不开
&gt;&gt; So Peter, we both love Lisp as a programming language.
那么 Peter 我们都喜欢 LISP 这种编程语言
What do you think that makes it special?
你觉得是什么让它与众不同呢？
&gt;&gt; I would say that today, Lisp is no longer really special.
我觉得时至今日 LISP 已经不再特殊了
But to me, that means that Lisp won.
但对我而言 这意味着 LISP 大获成功
It influenced all these other languages into adopting the key features.
因为它影响了其它所有语言 让其它语言都采用了 LISP 的关键特征
What things are they?
比如说
Well, a rich collection of data types, a read-eval-print loop, the notion
丰富的数据类型、读取-求值-输出循环、
of debugging a running program and being able to easily inspect the data.
调试运行程序的理念、可轻松检查数据的功能、
Preference for lots of functions, many without side effects,
它的诸多函数偏好 其中很多函数还没有副作用、
object orientation and inheritance if you want it.
面向对象、如果需要还能继承
All these things were unique to Lisp, but now they're in most languages.
这些特质曾经都独属于 LISP 但现在大多数语言都有
&gt;&gt; I think the one thing that hasn't caught on in other languages was
我觉得其它语言还没有引进的一点
the ability to define rich macros.
是强大的宏定义能力
Some languages have a limited macro capability.
有些语言也能定义宏 但能力有限
Lisp really went much farther.
可 LISP 能做的就多了
But that hasn't moved into current date languages yet.
不过它还没有转变成当代的数据语言
&gt;&gt; So when we first talked about my preparing this course, you convinced me
所以我们第一次探讨我要怎么准备这堂课时 你说服我
to use Python for the assignments, a language I didn't know at the time.
在作业里使用 Python 我那个时候还不知道这门语言呢
Why do you think Python is good for teaching this course?
为什么你觉得 Python 有利于这门课呢？
&gt;&gt; Well, when Stuart and I wrote the book, we didn't want to impose
当我和 Stuart 在写那本书时 我们不想强迫
a programming language choice on the reader or the instructor.
读者或讲师使用特定的编程语言
And so we just used a pseudo-code in the algorithms in the book.
所以书里的算法用的都是伪代码
We made up a format, and then we provided Lisp implementations for
我们确定了代码格式 然后在网上
the code online.
提供 LISP 的代码实现版本
Over time, fewer and fewer students knew Lisp, so
慢慢地 知道 LISP 的学员越来越少
I decided I would have to rewrite the code in a language.
所以我决定用一种编程语言来重写代码
And I wanted one that would be as close to the pseudo-code as possible,
我想找一种尽可能接近伪代码的语言
popular enough that many students would know it.
要足够流行 那样知道它的学员才多
And easy enough so that if a student didn't know it,
又要足够简单 那样就算学员不懂得这门语言
they'd still be able to understand it and pick it up quickly.
也能够很快理解并将它学起来
And so I surveyed all the languages, and
所以我对所有语言进行了一番调查
Python seemed to be by far the best choice.
发现 Python 似乎是目前的最佳选择
Somehow, Guido and we were in sync.
而不知道为何 Guido 和我们不谋而合
And we thought of the same pseudo-code, more or less,
我们想用一门语言代替伪代码 这种考虑
as he thought of as a language.
多多少少和他想的一样
And so that worked out well.
所以最后我们就用 Python 了
&gt;&gt; Cool, thank you.
好极了 谢谢